Finding Aid for a Collection of Ethiopic Manuscripts LSC.0937
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Title (Romanized): Salamta, Nagara Haymanot, Malek'a Gabre'él, Mahlet ?egé, Saqoqawa Denegel Uniform title: Maleke Title (English): Greetings, part of The Beauty of Creation, Image of St. Gabriel, Canticle of the Flower, Lamentation of the Virgin, Greetings of St. Michael., 119th.c.; Manuscript number: 48; Layout: Two columns per page, twenty three lines of text per page. Binding: wooden boards with no leather cover, string binding Velum, 102 pages Size: 158 mm x 92 mm x 25 mm The manuscript is composed of six quires of eight leaves each and one quire of four leaves. Text is in black ink and the beginning of the book and each prayer is in red ink. Color illustrations of saints. (Box 10)
- Title (Romanized): Marbabeta Salomon Uniform title: Magical prayers Title (English): Prayer of King Solomon for Catching Demons (Marbabta Solomon)., 19th.; Manuscript number: 49; Vellum, Scroll Layout: one column on a scroll composed with three strips of vellum in magic scroll format. Size: 1495 mm x 86 mm The text is in black ink. The beginging of each prayer and the name of the owner and dvine names are in red ink. Some illustrations. (Box 11)
  Aqba Giyorgis is the owner
  The scroll contains the magical prayer of King Solomon for catching demons. Marbabeta Solomon literally means "Net of Solomon." Healing images are common in most magical prayers. The prayer in this manuscript protects the owner from the hand of his enemies, from evil spirits which come as lions or tigers, and from other diseases.
- Title (Romanized): Marbabeta Salomon, ?alota Susnyos Uniform title: Magical prayers Title (English): Prayer of King Solomon for Catching of Demons, Prayer of Susneyos., 18th. C.; Manuscript number: 50; Vellum, Scroll Layout: one column on a scroll composed with strips of vellum in magic scroll format. Size: 1600 mm x 115 mm Text in black ink. Names of the saints, the beginning of each prayer, the names of the owners are in red ink Some illustrations. (Box 11)
  The owners of the scrolls are Walata Muse and Askala Mareyam (both of them are women).
  Magical prayer attributed to King Solomon for catching demnons. The scroll also includes the well-known magical prayer of Susneyos.
- Title (Romanized): ?alot ba?eneta Ma?esaromu la- Agan?ent Uniform title: Magical prayer Title (English): Prayer about binding of Demons. Prayer of St. Susneyos., 19th.; Manuscript number: 51; Vellum, Scroll Size: 1685 mm x 95 mm Layout: one column on a scroll composed with three strips of vellum in magic scroll format. The text is in black ink. The beginning of each prayer, divine names, and owner's name are in red ink. Some illustrations (Box 11)
  The owner's name is listed as Walata Mareyam
  Magical prayer for binding of the demons. The Prayer of Susneyos is a well-known magical prayer against children's diseases.
- Title (Romanized): ?alot ba?eneta Ma?esara Agan?ent Uniform title: Magical Prayers Title (English): Prayer for the Binding of Demons, Prayer of Susneyos., 20th. C.; Manuscript number: 52; Vellum, scroll Layout: one column on a scroll composed with three strips of vellum in magic scroll format. Size: 1515 mm x 95 mm Text in black ink. Saints and owners' names and the beginning of each prayer are in red ink. Some illustrations. (Box 11)
  The owner of this scroll is Wallata Eyasus.
- Title (Romanized): ?alot ba?eneta Ma?esara Agan?ent Uniform title: Magical Prayers Title (English): Prayer for the Binding of Demons., 18th c.; Manuscript number: 53; Vellum, scroll Layout: one column on a scroll composed with two strips of vellum in magic scroll format. Size: 1240 mm x 90 mm Text in black ink. Saints and owners' names and the beginning of each prayer are in red ink. Some illustrations. (Box 11)
  The owner of this scroll is Waleda Tenesa'e (Lagase).
- Title (Romanized): ?alot ba?eneta Ma?esara Agan?ent Uniform title: Magical Prayer Title (English): Prayer for the binding of demons., 19th. C.; Manuscript number: 54; Vellum, Scroll Layout: one column on a scroll composed with two strips of vellum in magic scroll format. Size: 1864 mm x 100 mm Text in black ink. The beginning of prayer and the name of the owner are in red ink. Some illustrations. (Box 11)
  The owner of the scroll is Amata Egzi'abeher or Belaynesh (the secular name) and Walata Mareyam
  Magical prayer against demons of blood and miscarriage.
- Title (Romanized): ?alot ba?eneta ma'esaromu la'aganenet Uniform title: Magical prayers Title (English): Prayer for the binding of demons., 18th.; Manuscript number: 55; Vellum, scroll Layout: one column on a scroll composed with two strips of vellum in magic scroll format. Size: 1815 mm x 108 mm Text in black ink, the beginning of each prayer and the name of the owner are in red ink. (Box 11)
  The owner of the scroll is Zawaleda Mareyam.
  Magical prayers for the binding of demons and against ayenat and eplipsy, which confuse the mind. The scroll also has a magical prayer attributed to King Solomon.
- Title (Romanized): ?alot ba?enta Ma'esara bareya walégéwon Uniform title: Magical prayers Title (English): Prayer for the Binding of Bareya and Legion., Early 19th. C.; Manuscript number: 56; Vellum, scroll Layout: one column on a scroll composed with four strips of vellum in magic scroll format. Size: 1930 mm x 105 mm Text in black ink, the beginning of each prayer is in red ink. Some illustrations (Box 11)
  The owner of the scroll is Walata Heyewat or Tabayen (Tabayen is the secular name).
  Magical prayer for a woman (probably mother of infant baby) to protect from epilepsy and miscarriage. Also includes well-known magical prayer to protect children from various diseases.
- Title (Romanized): ?alot ba?eneta Ayena tela Uniform title: Magical prayers Title (English):Prayers against Evil Eye., 19th c.; Manuscript number: 57; Vellum, scroll Layout: one column on a scroll composed with three strips of vellum in magic scroll format. Text is in black, special names in red ink. Size: 1725 mm x 100 mm Some illustrations. (Box 11)
  The owner of the manuscript is Eheta Mika'el Awaga (a woman).
  Magical prayer against evil eye and different diseases. The scroll contains part of the first chapter of the Gospel of John
- Title (Romanized): ?alot s'elat wa'astabequ'ot Uniform title: Collection of Prayers Title (English): Prayers, Petitions, and Supplications., 19th c.; Manuscript number: 58; Layout: Two columns per page, seventeen lines of text per page. Vellum, 338 pages Size: 180 mm x 170 mm x 75 mm Binding is wooden boards with no leather cover; string binding. The manuscript is composed of one quire of four leaves each, two quires of eight leaves each, one quire of twelve leaves, fourteen quires of ten leaves each. The text is in black ink. The beginning of each prayer and the name of the owner is in red ink. No illustrations. (Box 11)
  The original owner's name was erased repeatedly and replaced with the last owner, "Kefla Mareyam" (passim, p. 336)
  Collection of prayers attributed to known church fathers.
- Title (Romanized): Ma?ehafa Ziq, Malek'a Sellasé Uniform title: Church Hymns Title (English): Book of Ziq, Image of the Trinity., 20th.; Manuscript number: 59; Layout: One column of text, fifteen or sixteen lines of text per page Vellum, 176 pages Size: 130 mm x 100 mm x 36 mm Binding: wooden boards, in loose sewn cloth cover, in leather case with strap. Text is in black ink, with the names of people and the divine in red ink. With musical notation. The manuscript is composed of two quires of eight pages, eight quires of ten pages. No illustrations. (Box 12)
  The owner's name is erased on p. 175, but elsewhere retained as Takela Haymanot Waleda Mareyam (p. 158)
- Title (Romanized): ?oma Degwa Uniform title: Deguwa Title (English): Hymns for Lent., 19th.; Manuscript number: 60; Vellum, 232 pages Layout: Two columns per page, twenty lines of text per page Binding: Wooden boards with leather case Size: 180mm x 137mm x 47mm The manuscript is composed of two quires of four leaves, one quire of eight leaves, two quires of twelve leaves and eight quires of ten leaves each. The text is in black ink. The name of each section of the song is in red ink (Box 12)
  The manuscript contains Soma Deguwa, the Lenten hymns of St. Yared the Musician.
  Hymns for the Lenten season. St.Yared the Musician, the author of these hymns, divided the Lenten season into eight weeks. Almost all of the hymns are about the teaching and miracles of Jesus. The hymns discuss the teaching of Jesus in the Synagogue, his cleaning of the temple, his miracle of healing paralysis, his parable of the faithful servant, the discussion with Nicodimus, his teaching about his second coming, his glorious entrance into Jerusalem, his last days at Jerusalem, and his crucifixion.
- Title (Romanized): Malek'a Mareyam, Malek'a Madehane Alam, Malek'a Mika?él, Malek'a Gaberél, Malek'a Giyorgis Uniform title: Praise for Saints (Malek'e) Title (English): Image of Mary, Image of the Savior of the World, Image of St. Michael, Image of St.Gabriel, Image of St. George., 20 c.; Manuscript number: 61; Layout: two columns per page, twelve lines of text per page Vellum, 134 pages Binding: wooden boards with red stamped leather cover; inside leather case with strap Size: 128 mm x 95 mm x 32 mm The manuscript is composed of eight quires of eight leaves each. One quire has four blank leaves. The text is in black ink. The beginning of each 'malk' and 'salamta' and the name of the saints are in red ink. Decorative border, but no illustrations. (Box 13)
- Title (Romanized): Masehafa Ziq Uniform title: Church Hymns Title (English): The Book of Ziq., 19th. C.; Manuscript number: 62; Layout: One column per page, fifteen lines of text per page Vellum, 284 pages Binding is wooden board. Size: 143mm x 105mm x 75 The manuscript is composed of seventeen quires of eight leaves. The text is in black ink. The name of each greeting ('salamta') and saints' names are in red ink. Musical notations throughout, above each line of the hymn. Illustrations: none (Box 13)
  Authored by various Ethiopian scholars, mostly from the Gondar region. The hymns are sung following the 'malek' image assigned to be sung that day. Based on this interpretation, some scholars say that "Ziq" means "below," in Amharic "'zeq belo." Dillmann suggested that "ziq" derived from "zarziq," which means "condensed or collected works," see Kay Kaufman Shelemay and Peter Jeffery.
  Ziq is the collection of hymns praising God, Mary, and the saints. Following each malek assigned for that day, the ziq hymns will follow. Most of the ziq hymns come from other liturgical books, saints' lives, or the bible.
- Title (Romanized): Dawit ?alota Nabiyat,Weddasé Maryam, Anqa?a Berhan,Malek'a Gaber?él Uniform title: Psalter Title (English): Psalter and Canticles of New and Old Testaments Praise of Mary, The Gate of the Light; Image of Gabriel., 17th.; Manuscript number: 63; Vellum, 346 Pages Layout: one column on vellum; 19 lines of text per page. Praise of Mary and Gate of the light in two columns 19 lines of text per page. Pages 346 (started from page 17 assuming the first missing quire is eight leaves. Size: 140mm x 120 x 78mm Binding: wooden boards Text in black ink, some names and titles of the chapters are in red. The manuscript is composed of quires of eight leaves each. The front board is broken and sewn. The first quire ( pp1-16) is missing. Parts of one quire (including pp. 313 on the Praises of Mary) are inserted incorrectly in the manuscript. They appear earlier than they should. This misplacement probably happened in Ethiopia when the very old manuscript was rebound.
  Collection of Psalms, biblical canticles, and also praise hymns about Mary (attributed to St. Ephram of Syria [400s] and St. Yared of Ethiopia [600s])
- Title (Romanized): Ra'eya Maryam, Lefafa ?edqe, Ta'amra Mika'el Uniform title: Gadel Title (English): The Lives of Abba Zamika'el and Gabra Krestos, The Vision of Mary, The Bandlet of Righteousness, The Miracle of St. Michael., late 16th.; Manuscript number: 64; Vellum, 206 pages, 103ff Two columns, eighteen lines of text per page (the Miracle of St. Michael is 24 lines per page). Size: 178mm x 160mm x 49mm Binding is wooden boards with stamped leather back. The majority of the manuscript (Gadela Zamika'el and Gadela Gabera Keresetose) is composed of quires of eight leaves each. The text is in black ink; the name of God, angels, and saints, including the scribes and the owners, and the first line of each book, is in red ink. The books of Gadela Abba Zemikael and Gadela Gabera Keresetos are written in the same hand. Colophons: ff. 53, is a supplement to the hagiography called Salameta (greeting) to Gabera Keresetos ff. 101-102, is a list of the abbots who came before and after Zemikael (Aregawi) written in a second hand. ff.78-79 Bandlet of Righteousness is written in raqiq ( small hand writing) Images: f.1r, is a miniature representing Abba Zamika'el (Aragawi) f.54 is a miniature of Gabera Keresetos surrounded by dogs and with white leprosy spots (very important early representation of leprosy) f.1v is in English handwriting in ink and says " Taken from King Theodores arsenal [parts of word obscured] at Magdala after the fall of the place. 14th April 1868"
  The Life of Abba Zemike'el is well known because of the subject of the book, Abba Zamike'el, who was the founder of the great monastery of Dabra Damo. He is one of the Nine Saints of the fifth century who started the monastic movement in Ethiopia. Since the foundation of Dabra Damo, which is located in the Tigray Province, Abba Zamike'el has been considered the father of Ethiopian monastic life. The most respected monastic leaders included Abba Eyasus Mo'a and Abba Takela Haymanot, who not only made their monastic vows at Dabra Damo, but also considered themselves as the heirs of Abba Zamike'el. The Life of Abba Zamike'el is a very important 'gadel' (hagiography) which tries to explain how the celebrated monastic leader came to Ethiopia and founded the famous monastery. The gadel tells the story of Abba Zamike'el, the fourth generation after Saint Anthony and Saint Makars. Zamike'el was the son of King Isaac and Queen Edna of Rome, but he fled from his royal palace, and went to Abba Pachomius, founder of the first communal monastery of the Christian faith, and Zamike'el went to Axum carried on the wings of the angel. The book also narrates his struggle with the great serpent, which was considered by the local people of Dabera Damo as a god. The snake submitted and then took Zamike'el to the top of the mountain, where Zamike'el founded the monastery of Dabra Damo. Then King Gabara Maskal, son of King Kaleb, visited Dabra Damo. There is also the visitation of St. Yered the musician.
  The second book is about the life of St. Gabera Keresetose who is known in the rest of the world as St. Alexi. In Ethiopia, St Gabera Keresetose is the patron saint of the rejected and out-cast people. The uniqueness of this manuscript, as the late Professor Leslau and Professor Richard Pankhurst said, is the very beautiful miniature which sheds some light not only on medieval Ethiopian painting but also the attitude of people towards the victims of leprosy disease.
  In f.31v, 50v, 51r, 78r, the scribe mentions the owner Wolda Mareyam. Adara Giyoregis, inserted his name above the name of Wolda Mareyam.
  Compilation of important Ethiopian texts. Copied after 1632 (when the Portuguese were expelled). The first book in the compliation is the Life of Abba Zamika'el (Aragawi) discusses the life of Abba Zamika'el. He is one of the Nine Saints of the fifth century and a leader among those saints. Abba Zamika'el is the founder of the Dabra Damo monastery. The second book in the compliation is the Life of Gabera Keresetos, which describes the acetic life of Gabera Keresetos, the son of King Theodosius of Constantinople, and what happened after he ran away on his wedding night. The other books are, in order,The Vision of Mary, The Bandlet of Righteousness, The Miracle of St. Michael, for a total of five books.